This is probably the most important
video I'll ever make. I hope it will
change your life the same way that
researching it changed mine. I used to
think that working, saving, and
investing were all about getting as much
money as possible. Don't get me wrong,
money is a powerful tool. We need at
least enough money to live, and money
can solve some problems, but more money
is not in and of itself the main goal of
personal finance.
Personal finance is about funding a good
[snorts] life, which is subjective. But,
there is a lot of evidence about what,
generally speaking, constitutes a life
that people will evaluate as good. The
crazy thing is that a lot of the common
perceptions about what makes life good
are at odds with reality. I'm Ben Felix,
Chief Investment Officer at PWL Capital,
and I'm going to tell you about the
ingredients to a good life.
This might seem like a weird topic for a
Chief Investment Officer to cover, but
how you spend your time and money and
how you invest are informed by the life
you want to live. Think about some of
the big questions that people have to
answer every day. Is a higher-paying job
with longer hours and more stress worth
it? Is YOLOing on this stock trade for a
small chance of a big win worth the
risk? How should you prioritize saving
for the future against enjoying life
today? Should you rent or own your home?
Should you buy a cottage? Does it make
sense to pay for a house cleaner or meal
delivery? These are important questions
that can't be answered in a spreadsheet.
The thing is, though, and this is what I
think gets missed, there is a lot more
to a good life than a higher income and
more wealth. A good life is subjective.
My good life is not necessarily your
good life, but there's lots of research
on what does and does not tend to
contribute to good lives for most
people. The research on this is positive
rather than normative. That means it
doesn't tell people specifically what to
do. It examines empirically what tends
to make people evaluate their lives as
good. It's like giving you the
ingredients, but not the exact recipe to
a good life. You have to come up with
your own recipe. When we're talking
about a good life, broadly speaking,
there are two ways to measure it:
experienced or hedonic happiness and
reflective or eudemonic happiness. You
know experienced happiness when you feel
it, it's how you'd answer the question
how do you feel right now or how did you
feel yesterday? Reflective happiness is
related to how you evaluate your life.
It's how you'd answer the question how
do you rate your current life on a scale
where zero is the worst possible life
for you and 10 is the best possible life
for you. There's a very clear
distinction between feeling good right
now and evaluating your life as good
overall when you reflect on it, but both
are important to what I would call a
good life.
For example, you could have a life that
you evaluate positively when you step
back and think about it because you have
a good job, a nice house, maybe a
family, but you're stressed out through
most of the day and you're kind of
miserable. Or you could spend all day
every day drinking beer in a hot tub,
having a great time, but be disappointed
in your life when you step back and
reflect on your overall position. That
tension between the two types of
happiness makes defining a good life
kind of complicated, but there is a
model from the field of positive
psychology, the PERMA V model, which is
a model of human well-being that goes a
long way to organizing it. The factors
in the model don't have optimal
allocations, like it's not like
Markowitz portfolio theory,
for any individual, they just tell us
what tends to contribute to well-being.
The factors are positive emotion,
engagement, relationships, meaning,
accomplishment, and vitality, which was
added later. Positive emotion is feeling
good, you know when you feel it, like
eating a good meal or enjoying a walk
outside. Engagement is getting lost in a
challenging task that matches your
skills, known as a state of flow.
Relationships is having strong, reliable
relationships with friends and family.
Meaning is belonging to and serving
something bigger than yourself, like
being involved with your community or
for some people a religious group.
Accomplishment is achieving hard things
that are pursued for their own sake. A
classic example is mountaineering. It
kind of sucks to do, but you feel great
once you reach the summit and people do
it just to achieve it. Vitality, which I
mentioned was added later, is basically
eating well, sleeping well, and
exercising. A lot of people get stuck in
the trap of thinking that if they can
just get a big promotion at work, win
big on a stock trade, or win the
lottery, that their life will just
become good. But, that's not how it
typically works. And the pursuit of
money itself can actually have
unfavorable implications. There's no
doubt that we need a certain level of
income to live, but beyond that, money
and a good life have a bit of a
complicated relationship. There was an
influential 2010 study on a US sample
that found that life evaluation rises
steadily with income, while experienced
happiness rises with income up to about
$75,000 and then plateaus. That would be
around $112,000 US dollars today.
The authors conclude that high income
buys life satisfaction, but not
happiness. So, like life evaluation, but
not not experienced happiness. And that
low income is associated with low both
low life evaluation and low emotional
well-being. Then there's a 2018 study
that identified what they called points
of income satiation, above which
experienced happiness and life
evaluation stopped increasing in their
sample. The income satiation point for
life evaluation was about $105,000 for
North America in the study, which is
around $137,000 today. While experienced
happiness was about $65,000
or $85,000 today, just based on
inflation. In this study, some parts of
the world, including North America,
where I am, see a decline in life
evaluation at the highest levels of
income. The authors suggest that
individuals with higher incomes may be
less happy, not due to their higher
incomes, which why would that make you
unhappy? But, due to having more demands
on their time, less time for leisure
activities, an increase in materialistic
values, increased social comparison,
which I'll talk more about later, and
other life changes associated with
higher incomes, like living in a more
expensive neighborhood, which,
counterintuitively, is not great for
happiness. A 2021 study on a US sample
using real-time reports through a
smartphone app that asked multiple times
per day, "How do you feel right now?"
finds that both experienced and
reflective happiness do increase with
high income with no observed satiation
point. These results suggest that higher
incomes are associated with both feeling
better day-to-day and being more
satisfied with life overall. To
reconcile their findings, the authors
This is a pretty cool thing. The authors
of the 2010 and 2021 studies teamed up
for a 2023 paper that they called an
adversarial collaboration. So, they had
these conflicting results, and they
actually got together and tried to
reconcile. So, they re-examined each
other's results, and they worked toward
an understanding of why there were such
significant differences. They found that
happier people experience increased
well-being at higher levels of income,
but less happy people do see that
happiness plateau at higher levels of
income. So, happy people, your your
happiness keeps increasing with income.
People who are are not happy, generally,
uh their income that their happiness
does increase with income up to a point,
but then it plateaus like that original
study found.
Now, important points to note on these
studies is that they're looking at the
relationship between log-scale income
and happiness. I think this is often
missed in these discussions. That means
that each point on the income scale is a
doubling of income,
not a linear increase. So, we're not
talking about getting a an inflation
raise. We're talking about doubling your
income. And even with those big jumps in
income, the relationship between income
and happiness is is weak. The
correlation between average happiness
and log income is 0.09 in the experience
sampling data, and the difference
between the medians of happiness at
household incomes of $15,000 and
$250,000
is about five points on a 100-point
scale. These are small differences. The
2010 paper compares income to other
elements of of life to see how they
affect happiness relative to each other,
and finds that an approximately fourfold
difference in income is about equal to
the effect of being a caregiver for a
disabled or elderly family member. It's
about twice as large as the effect of
being married, and about equal to the
effect of a weekend, and less than a
third as large as the effect of a
headache.
Given the small effect, it's not
surprising that people tend to
overestimate how much happier they would
be with a higher income. I think people
often get stuck in that trap. If only my
income were higher. Even the wealthiest
households tend to believe that they
would need a lot more wealth in order to
be perfectly happy. Which is like it's
crazy. People focused on extrinsic
objectives like money, fame, and image
as opposed to intrinsic objectives like
growth, intimacy, and community tend to
be less happy in general and tend to
overestimate the emotional benefits of
achieving their extrinsic goals. I think
we can conclude that while having more
money is good, it's not that good with
respect to well-being and happiness. And
the pursuit of money for its own sake is
actually likely to be detrimental to
living a good life. Incredibly, across
all these studies, the researchers found
that the happiest participants were
subscribed to this YouTube channel.
They didn't actually find that, but you
should still subscribe to this channel.
All of this makes setting financial
goals, designing the life you want to
live a bit of a minefield, and it's
compounded by the fact that people are
really bad at predicting what will make
them happy in the future. A big reason
is adaptation. People generally adapt
quickly to changes in their life
circumstances, even to big financial
changes like winning the lottery. Big
financial goals like buying a bigger
house or moving to a more expensive
neighborhood might give you a short-term
burst of happiness, but will likely fade
quickly. This is the hedonic treadmill
we've all heard about. Another issue is
that we tend to focus on one big thing
that we imagine in the future like
buying the house or a cottage or
reaching a retirement savings goal, but
we don't think enough about how those
things how achieving those things
will affect how we spend our time, which
is more predictive of happiness than
stable circumstances. A further
complication is that personalities,
values, and preferences change over
time, but people tend to believe that
they have recently become the person
that they will remain for the rest of
their lives. This is called the end of
history illusion. It's crazy. It's like
people today imagine that they're
they're stable. This is how they're
going to be for the rest of their lives
while also acknowledging that they have
changed significantly throughout their
lives. And and people of all ages have
this perception. It's a fascinating
phenomenon.
Uh so that's that's the end of history
illusion. Setting out to achieve some
big future goal that your current self
sets, like an early retirement or a
major purchase in the distant future,
might not end up resonating with your
future self. So you make sacrifices and
whatever. You you overcome obstacles to
achieve some big long-term goal, and
then you get there and you're like, "Oh,
this is maybe not what I actually
wanted." Or or maybe it didn't make me
make me as happy as I was expecting. So
given the challenges in predicting the
circumstances that will make us happy in
the future, and even knowing who we will
be as a person in the future, it can be
sensible to focus on how financial
decisions will affect how we spend our
time rather than striving to achieve a
perfectly imagined future, particularly
when the path to getting there makes
today unpleasant. It is important to
note that while people generally adapt
to their circumstances, good and bad,
some things are harder to adapt to.
Noise, especially variable or
intermittent noise, interferes with
concentration and increases stress, even
after years of commuting. People who
commute in traffic arrive at work with
higher levels of stress hormones. This
is relevant for anyone considering a
move further away from work or family,
introducing a longer commute to which
they will not adapt in order to get a
bigger house, which they will tend to
adapt to quickly. Not being in control
of your circumstances has a large
negative impact on happiness and life
satisfaction. Maintaining a feeling of
control may be relevant in the rent
versus buy decision for housing, which
I'll talk more about in a minute, and in
achieving financial independence.
Another sneaky drain on happiness is
social comparison, which can have
immediate impacts on your finances.
While we may not like to admit it, our
well-being is affected by how we compare
to those around us. And many people
maintain a lifestyle that is outside of
their means, driving down their savings
rate, and putting even the most affluent
households in precarious financial
positions, driven by social comparison.
Aside from avoiding those negative
circumstances and avoiding the issues
with social comparison, remember that
the elements of a good life are positive
emotion, engagement, relationships,
meaning, and accomplishment, plus
vitality. Money buys a bit of happiness,
but not as much as people expect, and
how we spend our time has a big impact
on our well-being. Let's apply these
ideas to some major financial decisions
that affect how people spend their time
and money. Time and money are somewhat
exchangeable. We can spend time working
to earn money, and we can spend money to
save time by outsourcing tasks or buying
time-saving products. Decisions about
the time-money trade-off are some of the
most impactful decisions that people can
make. Empirically, people who prioritize
time over money, meaning that they're
willing to sacrifice their money to have
more time by, for example, choosing to
work fewer hours and make less money
rather than more hours for more money,
are happier. They have greater social
connection, they have a better
relationship with their spouse, and
they're more likely to choose work that
they enjoy. Given the choice to spend
some money to save some time, or work a
little less to get some time back,
choosing time over money is generally a
good decision.
That leads to less money, which is the
fascinating thing about this stuff. A
worthwhile exercise is asking yourself
whether how you are spending your time
contributes to your version of a good
life, and if not, whether you can trade
money for time to fix it. Housing is
typically the largest single expense for
most households, and it's a basic human
need. Owning a home can offer stability,
particularly if you want to stay in a
specific area for a long time. It does
also give you more control over your
environment. I put a full-size
basketball hoop in my house, like a
glass backboard and everything. It's
kind of crazy. I would not have done
that in a rental. It I'm not going to
lie, it's pretty cool. However, I have
also enjoyed all of my past rentals with
no basketball hoop. There are gyms that
I can go to to play basketball. Broadly
speaking, based on studies in Canada and
Switzerland, owning a home does not make
homeowners happier than renters when you
control for all the other stuff that
could affect happiness. In an American
sample of 600 women, homeowners were not
happier than renters and spent less time
on enjoyable activities. In a German
sample, while homeownership did elevate
life satisfaction, it did so much less
than people anticipated it would when
they made the decision to buy the house.
Owning a home also affects how you spend
your time. I can tell you this with
certainty as a homeowner. It's like
having a second job, even if you
outsource a lot of the work. It's no
joke. Some people love that stuff, which
great for them. I I actually don't mind
house maintenance stuff, but I don't
like it when it takes away from the time
I want to use to do things that I like
more. As a renter, you just wash your
hands of that stuff. You call the
landlord and it gets fixed. For anyone
making the rent versus own decision for
housing, the notion that it will improve
your life should be approached with
caution. A common related decision is
buying a cottage. Cottages are often
viewed as a place for family to gather,
sometimes for generations, which does
hit on the relationships element of a
good life. Being outside in nature is
also related to positive emotion.
However, it's important to think about
the details. Who are you going to invite
to the cottage? What if some family
members don't get along? Who will take
care of the maintenance? How bad will
traffic be leaving the city on Friday
afternoons with two kids in the
backseat? These details will likely be
more predictive of happiness than the
fact that you own the cottage. When
deciding how to spend discretionary
money, we have a choice between, broadly
speaking, experiences and things.
Spending on experiences, when they are
positive, is more impactful to
increasing happiness than spending on
things, though negative experiences have
the opposite effect. If we come back to
the PERMA model, this makes a lot of
sense. People are happy when they're
engaged in what they're doing and
experiences can provide that a kind of
engagement. Experiences are more likely
than things to be shared with other
people, and strong relationships are
important to happiness. Reflecting on
past experiences enhances mood more than
reflecting on past material purchases,
and people tend to remember and
anticipate experiences more than things.
It's also harder to adapt to experiences
than things, since each experience is
unique while things are static. Not all
things are bad to spend money on, but I
think it's worth asking how the thing
will contribute to your good life. The
biggest goals for most people are
financial independence and financial
security. This makes sense because they
put you in control, at least as in
control as we can be, in life. Still
lots of unpredictable stuff. But, saving
for financial independence, which is
necessary for most people, it is the
right objective to have. It's competing
with spending today.
That present versus future trade-off is
another one of the biggest decisions
that people make every day. Achieving
financial sooner is good, all else
equal, but it has to be balanced against
living the life that you want today.
It's also worth considering that as long
as you're able to do work that you
enjoy, work has a lot of benefits. It
can contribute to engagement, meaning,
and accomplishment. Some studies show
that people who retire lose their sense
of purpose, while other studies do show
that people leaving lower income and
less satisfying jobs gain a sense of
purpose.
This matters because planning to work
longer at a job that you enjoy makes
more spending available today. I'm not
saying you should spend all your money
today, but it's important to carefully
consider the type of work that you do,
how long you plan to work, and how that
will impact your spending and saving
decisions. One of the best ways to deal
with the inability to predict what will
make us happy in the future is to make
more frequent, small experiential
purchases rather than fewer large
material ones, particularly when they
contribute to positive emotion,
which could be things like savoring a
coffee, engagement, which could be
spending on a hobby, relationships,
which could be taking a friend out to
dinner, meaning, which could be spending
on your community, and accomplishment,
which could be something like paying for
a course that you want to complete.
Knowing that how we spend our time is
more predictive of happiness than how we
spend our money, a simple test for
expenses is to think about how it will
affect how you spend your time and
whether that relates to your definition
of a good life. Another longer-term lens
that can help us understand what tends
to constitute a good life is regret.
People like to say they they live with
no regrets, but regret is powerful.
Unlike other negative emotions, regret
cannot be experienced without having
made a choice. In research for his book
on regret, Dan Pink found in a large US
sample that people's regrets most
commonly involve family, romantic
partners, education, career, finances,
and health. And most people regret their
inactions more than their actions. In an
academic paper on regret, the authors
find in a representative US sample that
regrets involving romance are the most
common, followed by family, education,
career, finances, and parenting. Over
time, regrets about action tend to
dissipate. Doing something, I Oh, I did
a thing and I regret it. That tends to
go away. Regrets about inaction, that
something that you did not do that you
wish you had done, those tend to linger.
They don't tend to go away. That can be
relevant for financial decisions where
playing it safe today on things like
starting a business or declining an
exciting job offer lead to missed
opportunities. Those types of inactions
can feel kind of painless in the short
run. Like, "No, I'm not going to take
the job."
Uh "No, I'm not going to start the
business." But those are the types of
regrets that lead to more long-term pain
that it's harder to recover from. You
look back and think, "Oh, if only I had
done that, things would have been
different."
A lot of regret comes back to
compounding small decisions day-to-day
that lead to a state that is hard to
reverse in the future.
Eating poorly and not saving enough for
are examples where the immediate effect
is minimal. You eat a burger instead of
a salad, whatever. Uh or you you spend
your money instead of saving it today.
So, it's it's not a big deal day-to-day,
but eventually it's too late to reverse
heart disease or build up your
retirement savings when you're 60 years
old.
Part of the problem here is that the
human brain is not wired to think about
the effects of compounding, making the
long-term effects of those daily small
decisions really hard for us to process.
We don't realize how impactful those
small decisions are going to be until
it's too late to do something about it.
Okay, with all that background on what
contributes to a good life, the last
thing I need to talk about is setting
goals. If I ask you what your goals are,
you probably you be able to tell me even
if you think you can. You might tell me
your goals,
uh but when prompted properly, people
often realize that their goals, the ones
that they state when I ask you the
question, fall short of what they
actually care about. There are a couple
ways to elicit more meaningful goals. A
big one is using categorical prompts,
showing people categories that financial
goals might fit into. Another is the use
of a master list, a comprehensive list
of goals collected from many other
people who have set their own goals.
In 2022, I conducted a study where I
asked 310 people,
largely listeners of uh of my podcast,
to write down their goals. They were
then asked to double the list of goals
after the first pass, and they were then
presented with the PERMA-V model of
well-being as potential goal categories.
Again, PERMA-V stands for positive
emotion, engagement, relationships,
meaning, and accomplishment. When you
ask someone what their goals are, they
might say, "I want to retire." But when
you say goals might fit into these six
categories, they tend to come up with
more meaningful goals. They get closer
to what really matters. Using the data
from my study, Morningstar's behavioral
research team found using natural
language processing that after being
introduced to the PERMA-V model, people
tended to list deeper goals that
reflected their values rather than more
surface-level goals like wanting to
retire. My study also resulted in a
master list of goals that people can
still find on the PWL Capital website.
This master list can be used in addition
to the PERMA-V categorical prompts as
part of a structured goal-setting
process. Understanding your true goals
is important because the path to getting
there might be very different from the
path to achieving some other
surface-level goal or the uncharted path
of doing whatever feels right in the
moment. People are responsible for
making financial decisions, which
typically involve time and money
multiple times each day. This is not an
easy task since we are wired to make
quick decisions that result in
short-term pleasure and improve our
status relative to those around us, even
the noble objective of setting long-term
financial goals is easily sabotaged by
our inability to identify a complete set
of personally important objectives, and
our weak ability to know what will make
us happy in the future. Stepping back to
reflect on how our decisions will affect
life satisfaction and happiness requires
more effortful thought. A model to
understand what a good life looks like,
the PERMA model that I've talked about,
and a plan to achieve it. The first step
in finding a good life is finding a good
life. I hope this video is a starting
point.